A Guide to the Phoebus A.T. Levene papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA174
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Manuscripts, 1929; Box 9: 5" Hollinger boxes
  "Pincussen article" [1929 review, in German, by Levene. The following folders were found in a package, wrapped and tied in brown paper, and labeled "Pincussen article." The titles listed below were copied from the original folders, with some abridgement of section numbers/letters. They have been rearranged to simplify retrieval.].
  - General
    - Carbon copies of first draft (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - General index to nucleic acids (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - German galley (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Loose pages (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Note cards (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Rewritten copies, 2 folders (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
  - Manuscripts (in English)
    - Enzymes. Nucleases (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Mono- and polynucleotides (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Natural phosphatides (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Nucleoproteins (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Nucleosides (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Phosphatides (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Products of complete hydrolysis of Lecithin and Cephalin (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Products of intermediate hydrolysis of Lecithin and Cephalin (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Purinamidases 1) Prep, of Extracts 2) Analytical procedure (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Purindehydrase (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Purine derivatives (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Pyrimidine derivatives (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Pincussen article
    - [re pyrimidines] (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Synthesis of glycero-phosphoric acid (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Synthesis of lecithin and cephalin (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Notes And Notebooks, 5" Hollinger boxes
  - Bass notes on nucleic acids, 4 folders (Box 10, Folder 4-7)
  - Passoth notes, 2 folders (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
  - Ulpts, R. notebooks, 1924 October-November; 2 folders (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
- Scientific Reports, 1935-1939; 5" Hollinger box, 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 1)
  Stencilled copies of April reports to Board of Scientific Directors, RIMR.
- Unfinished mss, 5" Hollinger boxes
  [The material below was found tied together in folders and envelopes. The papers consist of manuscript drafts, data, and notes. The titles have been copied from the original labels; the folders have, however, been rearranged into alphabetical order by author, where a name was indicated, or by subject title. The last two folders appear to be an exception to the "unfinished" class, as they contain galleys as well as mss (work of A.L. Raymond, submitted from Caltech); also see folder 3].
  - Blanco. Water metabolism (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Christman, C.C., 1938-1939 May (Box 11, Folder 3)
    [But see note on cover: "Dr. Levene says this work has been published. May 1939"].
  - Clark - Work on Diazo Chitosaminic Acid Ethyl Ester (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Cortese. d-ribose (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Gilman Ms. - A.L. Raymond, Summer 1935 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Gilman article, Discards to be kept. Rotatory dispersion, 1936 October (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Haller. Introduction (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Haller, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Helberger - Crystalline pepsin, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Hill, Douglas C. Chromoproteins (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Levene and Bass. Racemization of gelatin (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Levene - Hill. The action of pyridine on sugars (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Levene - Meyer - Kuna. On the mode of union of the galacturonic residues in pectic acid, 1939-1941 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    [Not published. Also contains reprint and acceptance by Science of "Preliminary Note" on same subject, 1939].
  - Levene - Rothen. J. Chem. Phys, 1935 February (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Levene, Miscellaneous I-IV, 4 folders (Box 11, Folder 16-19)
- Unfinished mss
  - Mehltretter, 1937 June (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Meyer. Dissociation constants polyvalent sub (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Mori. Thio sugar (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Rothen paper, Discards, 1932 June (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Schmidt, Gerhard [Experiments on pancreas nucleic acid], 1938 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Simms, 1925 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Simms. Review of methods for calculating pK values (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Van der Hoeven. Purification of silica gel, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Walti. Acetoin, 1931 June (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Azido Propionic acid (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Chemical structure and optical activity (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Mechanism of the reaction of Walden inversion. Discarded pages, 1937 May (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - OH to NH₂ relationship (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Thyminic acid (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified rough drafts, circa 1936 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Raymond. The determination of carbon dioxide in fermenting mixtures. Rec'd publication, 1927 April 26; Ms. and galley (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Raymond and Winegarden. Co-zymase. A study of purification methods, circa 1927; Ms. and galley (Box 12, Folder 17)
- Manuscripts, 5" Hollinger boxes
  [The material in boxes 12-16 consists of manuscripts of P.A. Levene publications: 2 articles with A. Rothen, and the monograph on Nucleic Acids with L. Bass. Most of the mss. were in well-labeled 3-ring binders. The titles are taken from the original labels. C. Kopp, 13 Aug 1985].
  - Levene and Rothen. Optical activity and chemical structure. J. Org. Chem, 1936 March
    - Mss, miscellaneous (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - 2nd rough draft, 2 folders (Box 12, Folder 19-20)
    - Final yellows, 2 folders (Box 12, Folder 21-22)
    - Galley and tables. Ibid (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Levene and Rothen. Rotatory dispersion. Ch. 21 in Organic Chemistry, ed. H. Gilman, 1938
    - Rothen mss (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1st rough draft, 2 folders (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
    - Pre-final (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Final (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Copy-edited typescript (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Galleys. I. (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Galleys II. Ibid (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, 9 negatives 1 graph (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Levene and Bass. Nucleic Acids (Box 14)
    - untitled, 4 folders, holograph (Levene handwriting) (Box 14, Folder 3-6)
    - Corrected 1st draft. Chs. 1-8, 3 folders (Box 14, Folder 7-9)
    - Corrected 1st draft. Chs. 9-10. Ibid (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 2nd draft [re pyrimidines], 1 folder only (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - untitled, 9 folders, typescript (Box 15, Folder 3-11)
    - Copy-edited. Title, preface, pp. 1-75, 2 folders, typescript (Box 15, Folder 12-13)
    - Copy-edited. Title, preface, pp. 76-572, 7 folders, typescript (Box 16, Folder 1-7)
  - Manuscripts, miscellaneous.
    - Nucleic acids - Abderhalden (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - re optical activity, 1935-1936 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Nucleic Acids by P.A. Levene and Lawrence W. Bass. New York: The Chemical Catalog Co., 1931. Galleys and page proofs
    - Galley (corrected), 2 copies (Box 17, Folder 1-6)
    - Page proofs (corrected) (Box 17, Folder 7-9)
    - Page proof [Page 11 has note attached, "This page proof has been cut up by request of Dr. Levene (Dec. 3, 1931) to make lantern slides for lecture at Columbia Dec. 11, 1931"], 1931 December (Box 17, Folder 10-13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 17, Folder 14)
- Glass slides, unsorted, slides box, circa 80 slides (Box 18)
- P.A. Levene article in Dental Cosmos, "Sodium methylate as a substitute for sodium-potassium, and sugar lactones as a substitute for strong acids, both in the treatment of root canals." 63: 905-906 (1921), Photocopy.
  RUL-Interlibrary loan. Received February, 1985.
- Levene bas-relief by S. Konenkov, 1927; 1 print
  Hangs in RU Library. 26 March 1985.